<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-de.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="de" id="errata-changelog-4.2-de">

	<bookinfo>
 		<title>UCS@school 4.2 v6 Changelog</title>
		<!-- <subtitle>Changelog für das Update von UCS@school 4.2 v5 nach 4.2 v6</subtitle> -->
		<legalnotice>
			<literallayout>
Version 4.2 v6
Stand: 12. December 2017
			</literallayout>
			<literallayout lang="">
Alle Rechte vorbehalten./ All rights reserved.
(c) 2002-2017
Univention GmbH
Mary-Somerville-Straße 1
28359 Bremen
Deutschland
feedback@univention.de
			</literallayout>
			<para>
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="changelog:main">
		<title>&ucsUAS;-Update</title>
		<para>
			Dieses Dokument enthält die Changelogs mit den detaillierten Änderungsinformationen zum Update von &ucsUAS; von Version 4.2 v5 nach 4.2 v6.
			Sofern notwendig, werden wichtige Hinweise zum Update in einem separaten Abschnitt behandelt. Die Changelogs werden nur in Englisch
			gepflegt. Die Änderungsinformationen für vorherige Versionssprünge finden sich unter <ulink	url="https://docs.software-univention.de/"/>.
		</para>

		<section id="changelog:prepare">
			<title>Generelle Hinweise zum Update</title>
			<para>
				Während der Aktualisierung kann es zu Ausfällen von Diensten innerhalb der Domäne
				kommen. Aus diesem Grund sollte das Update innerhalb eines Wartungsfensters
				erfolgen. Grundsätzlich wird empfohlen das Update zunächst in einer Testumgebung
				einzuspielen und zu testen. Die Testumgebung sollte dabei identisch zur
				Produktivumgebung sein.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="changelog:changelogs" lang="en">
			<title>Changelog</title>
						<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-import" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-import</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A new experimental UMC module has been implemented that uses the experimental HTTP-API for importing users in UCS@school (<u:bug>45664</u:bug>, <u:bug>45659</u:bug>, <u:bug>45662</u:bug>, <u:bug>45660</u:bug>, <u:bug>45717</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-distribution" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-distribution</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>When collecting distributed materials, files are now stored into a directory <literal>Unterrichtsmaterial/<replaceable>PROJEKTNAME</replaceable>-Ergebnisse</literal>. The suffix for the name of that directory can be modified with the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/datadistribution/datadir/sender/project/suffix</envar> (default is "-Ergebnisse") (<u:bug>45572</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>When running a resync to recreate all netlogon scripts, the listener module now restarts the netlogon script generation daemon (<u:bug>45544</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-import" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-import</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>An experimental HTTP API for starting import jobs can now be installed (<u:bug>45844</u:bug> <u:bug>45024</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The configured user role is taken into account when searching for users (<u:bug>45044</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Configuration and code for reading and writing CSV data compatible with the HTTP-API was added (<u:bug>45342</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The script <command>ucs-school-testuser-import</command> mistakenly added new students to single letter classes that were disjoint with the classes of other testusers. This problem has been fixed (<u:bug>45436</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The import scripts for creating computers, networks, printers or groups do not create schools anymore. Previously if the CSV data contained a school which did not exists a broken OU structure was created. Now, if the OU is missing, please call <command>create_ou</command> prior to <command>import_computer</command>, <command>import_networks</command>, <command>import_printer</command> or <command>import_group</command> (<u:bug>34727</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Add a method in the HTTP-API which returns the permitted roles for school where a user can start an import (<u:bug>45717</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Various security concerns of the new HTTP-API have been eliminated (<u:bug>45713</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The maximum length of a username for teachers and staff is now 20. The student's username may not be longer than 15 characters to support the use of the exam mode and ensure a working windows login (<u:bug>45577</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The new UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/import/generate/user/attributes/no-overwrite</envar> is a whitespace separated list of LDAP attributes that the user import will not overwrite when their values are non-empty. This fixes a bug which made generated email adresses change on every import (<u:bug>45679</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Non-ASCII characters in <property>sourceUID</property> and <property>recordUID</property> are now handled correctly (<u:bug>45626</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-lib" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-lib</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>An internal improvement of the &ucsUAS; library: support was added for changing the base path when searching for hooks (<u:bug>45024</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>An internal improvement of the &ucsUAS; library: LDAP object classes for user objects are made available for permission checks during imports (<u:bug>45044</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A tool for modifying UCR list values was added (<u:bug>44627</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-selfservice-support" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-selfservice-support</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>This package provides a configuration to better integrate the self-service app in a UCS@school domain. It automatically sets the whitelist for user groups for all schools. This package should be installed on the DC master and DC backups only (<u:bug>44627</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-users" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-users</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The default state of the checkbox to force a password change on the next login may now be defined via UCR (<u:bug>42004</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>
