<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-de.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="de" id="errata-changelog-4.1-de">

	<bookinfo>
 		<title>UCS@school 4.1 R2 v10 Changelog</title>
		<!-- <subtitle>Changelog für das Update von UCS@school 4.1 R2 v9 nach 4.1 R2 v10</subtitle> -->
		<legalnotice>
			<literallayout>
Version 4.1 R2 v10
Stand: 17. März 2017
			</literallayout>
			<literallayout lang="">
Alle Rechte vorbehalten./ All rights reserved.
(c) 2002-2017
Univention GmbH
Mary-Somerville-Straße 1
28359 Bremen
Deutschland
feedback@univention.de
			</literallayout>
			<para>
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="changelog:main">
		<title>&ucsUAS;-Update</title>
		<para>
			Dieses Dokument enthält die Changelogs mit den detaillierten Änderungsinformationen zum Update von &ucsUAS; von Version 4.1 R2 v9 nach 4.1 R2 v10.
			Sofern notwendig, werden wichtige Hinweise zum Update in einem separaten Abschnitt behandelt. Die Changelogs werden nur in Englisch
			gepflegt. Die Änderungsinformationen für vorherige Versionssprünge finden sich unter <ulink	url="https://docs.software-univention.de/"/>.
		</para>

		<section id="changelog:prepare">
			<title>Generelle Hinweise zum Update</title>
			<para>
				Während der Aktualisierung kann es zu Ausfällen von Diensten innerhalb der Domäne
				kommen. Aus diesem Grund sollte das Update innerhalb eines Wartungsfensters
				erfolgen. Grundsätzlich wird empfohlen das Update zunächst in einer Testumgebung
				einzuspielen und zu testen. Die Testumgebung sollte dabei identisch zur
				Produktivumgebung sein.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="changelog:changelogs" lang="en">
			<title>Changelog</title>
						<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-wizards" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-wizards</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>Single user roles (student, teacher, staff, teachersAndStaff) can now be disabled in UMC module <guimenu>Users (schools)</guimenu> via the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/wizards/schoolwizards/users/roles/disabled</envar> (<u:bug>42349</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A logic error has been fixed that prevented the removal of a OU-overlapping user account from a secondary OU (<u:bug>43170</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Changes within the UCS@school lib required some internal adjustments to this package (<u:bug>41910</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-csv-import" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-csv-import</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>Single user roles (student, teacher, staff, teachersAndStaff) can now be disabled in UMC module <guimenu>CSV import</guimenu> via the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/csvimport/users/roles/disabled</envar> (<u:bug>41387</u:bug>) .</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A broken code path that has never been executed has been removed from the postinst script of package <package>ucs-school-umc-csv-import</package> (<u:bug>41418</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-webproxy" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-webproxy</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The file <filename>wpad.dat</filename> for browser proxy configuration is now created as a symlink to <filename>proxy.pac</filename> (<u:bug>31728</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The name of the folder link on the user's desktop can now be set via UCR: <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/shares_foldername</envar> defaults to <literal>Eigene Shares</literal>. If the special folders <literal>My Files</literal> and <literal>My Pictures</literal> are redirected from local profile path to the user's network home directory, the directory names of those folder within user's home directory may now be specified via UCR: <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/myshares/name</envar> defaults to <literal>Eigene Dateien</literal> and <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/mypictures/name</envar> defaults to <literal>Eigene Bilder</literal> (<u:bug>37256</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The icons of the folders created by the netlogon script can now be set: <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/shares_folder_icon</envar>, <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/my_files_link_icon</envar>, <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/other_links_icon</envar>. The name of the <literal>My Files</literal> directory within the folder, created by the netlogon script, can now be set via the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/my_files_link_name</envar> (<u:bug>41375</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Whitespace in the list of share names in the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/commonshares</envar> is now handled more securely (<u:bug>43504</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Certain elements of the user netlogon script can now be disabled. See UCR descriptions for <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/create_myfiles_link</envar>, <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/create_shortcuts</envar>, <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/create_teacher_umc_link</envar> and <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/disabled_share_links/*</envar>.  It is now possible to configure the path in which the directory for the links will be created by setting the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/shares_folder_parent_path</envar> (<u:bug>43526</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-helpdesk" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-helpdesk</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The category creation upon package installation does not fail anymore (<u:bug>38389</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-lib" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-lib</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>Add support for complete removal of a ou-overlapping user from a secondary school, including removal of all groups (<u:bug>41910</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Adjust UMC wizard to behavioral change in UCS@school lib (<u:bug>43170</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-computerroom" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-computerroom</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The computerroom module now supports web links that point directly to the computerroom supervision/screenshot page (<u:bug>42356</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:italc" lang="en">
				<title>Source package italc</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A segfault in the UMC module <guimenu>Computer room</guimenu> has been fixed which occurred during receiving a screenshot from a client's computer (<u:bug>43244</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A segfault in the UMC module <guimenu>Computer room</guimenu> could occur randomly when determining the current user on a windows client. The segfault has now been fixed (<u:bug>43092</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>
