<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-de.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="de" id="errata-changelog-4.2-de">

	<bookinfo>
 		<title>UCS@school 4.2 v4 Changelog</title>
		<!-- <subtitle>Changelog für das Update von UCS@school 4.2 v3 nach 4.2 v4</subtitle> -->
		<legalnotice>
			<literallayout>
Version 4.2 v4
Stand: 16. October 2017
			</literallayout>
			<literallayout lang="">
Alle Rechte vorbehalten./ All rights reserved.
(c) 2002-2017
Univention GmbH
Mary-Somerville-Straße 1
28359 Bremen
Deutschland
feedback@univention.de
			</literallayout>
			<para>
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="changelog:main">
		<title>&ucsUAS;-Update</title>
		<para>
			Dieses Dokument enthält die Changelogs mit den detaillierten Änderungsinformationen zum Update von &ucsUAS; von Version 4.2 v3 nach 4.2 v4.
			Sofern notwendig, werden wichtige Hinweise zum Update in einem separaten Abschnitt behandelt. Die Changelogs werden nur in Englisch
			gepflegt. Die Änderungsinformationen für vorherige Versionssprünge finden sich unter <ulink	url="https://docs.software-univention.de/"/>.
		</para>

		<section id="changelog:prepare">
			<title>Generelle Hinweise zum Update</title>
			<para>
				Während der Aktualisierung kann es zu Ausfällen von Diensten innerhalb der Domäne
				kommen. Aus diesem Grund sollte das Update innerhalb eines Wartungsfensters
				erfolgen. Grundsätzlich wird empfohlen das Update zunächst in einer Testumgebung
				einzuspielen und zu testen. Die Testumgebung sollte dabei identisch zur
				Produktivumgebung sein.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="changelog:changelogs" lang="en">
			<title>Changelog</title>
						<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-import" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-import</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A beta version of a new UCS@school import module has been implemented (<u:bug>45023</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The import UMC module supports login via SAML (<u:bug>45045</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-rooms" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-rooms</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A standby animation is now shown while the UMC module is creating or modifying school rooms (<u:bug>45512</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-s4-branch-site" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-s4-branch-site</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>UCR variables for the DNS mapping configuration are no longer overwritten or reset if an error during the LDAP connection happens in the Univention Directory Listener module, e.g. while changing the server password (<u:bug>45428</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-webproxy" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-webproxy</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A race condition in the caching mechanism for handling proxy groups has been fixed (<u:bug>45352</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-exam" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-exam</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The cleanup script <command>exam-and-room-cleanup</command> will now also remove computers accounts from the exam group (<u:bug>43978</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>In some &ucsUAS; environments students are member of a large number of groups. If these students take part of an exam, the exam mode copies all group memberships from the students to the corresponding exam users, by default. For performance and security reasons, it is now possible to blacklist groups from being taken over to exam users by defining a regular expression for group DNs (UCR variable <env>ucsschool/exam/group/ldap/blacklist/regex</env>) (<u:bug>45473</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The timeout for starting new exams has been raised from 5 minutes to 30 minutes (<u:bug>45980</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-printermoderation" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-printermoderation</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The print jobs of the currently logged-in teacher are now also displayed in the printermoderation UMC module (<u:bug>43704</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-radius-8021x" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-radius-802.1x</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A traceback has been fixed that may happened if <command>ucs-school-ntlm-auth</command> is called without <option>--stationId</option> option (<u:bug>45482</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-netlogon-user-logonscripts</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The generation of netlogon scripts for Windows users has been separated into a new daemon that is triggered via the Univention Directory Listener. This way, the LDAP replication should not be slowed down any longer by lots of LDAP changes relevant for netlogon script generation (<u:bug>42997</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The shortcuts to the users shares showed the wrong icons in Windows 10. This has been fixed. It is recommended, that the netlogon scripts are being recreated on each school server by calling the command <command>univention-directory-listener-ctrl resync ucs-school-user-logonscript</command> as user root. Otherwise the existing netlogon scripts still show the wrong icons under Windows 10. To deactivate the adjustment of the icon index of the file <filename>imageres.dll</filename>, set the UCR variable <envar>ucsschool/userlogon/fix-win10-icon-offset</envar> to <literal>false</literal> (<u:bug>45301</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-metapackage" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-metapackage</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>By default, the DHCP-DNS policy <emphasis>dhcp-dns-$OUNAME</emphasis> now also sets the domain name (<u:bug>42688</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-import" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-import</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>When run with the <option>--dry-run</option> option, the raised counter is not stored anymore in LDAP (<u:bug>44838</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A Python client library to use the experimental RESTful API was created (<u:bug>45022</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>An experimental RESTful API for starting import jobs can now be installed (<u:bug>4501945024</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The handling of <option>scheme:email</option> options during import of user has been improved: the <literal>COUNTER</literal> variables may now be used (<u:bug>44993</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The configured user role is taken into account when searching for users (<u:bug>45044</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Configuration and code for reading and writing CSV data compatible with the HTTP-API was added (<u:bug>45342</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>It is now possible to modify the attributes that are used for formatting user properties from a schema by creating hooks. An example is provided in <filename>/usr/share/doc/ucs-school-import/format_hook_example.py</filename> (<u:bug>42144</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The class generation of the test user creation script was fixed (<u:bug>45436</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>When creating a school, the DHCP server objects for the administrative DC Slave are now also created or moved into the DHCP service of the school in a multiserver environment (<u:bug>42687</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The school name is now checked case sensitively before importing a user (<u:bug>42456</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The tool <command>ucs-school-join-secondary-samba4</command> checks now if the school DC has the S4 SlavePDC service set (<u:bug>43311</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>By default, the DHCP-DNS policy <emphasis>dhcp-dns-$OUNAME</emphasis> now also sets the domain name (<u:bug>42688</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>The deletion behavior of <command>ucs-school-user-import</command> has been improved. It is now possible to define grace periods, after which the users who are scheduled to delete are automatically deactivated or deleted. If the <option>user_deletion:delete</option> or <option>user_deletion:expiration</option> options have been used, the import configuration must be adapted, otherwise the import will terminate with a configuration error. The new options are <option>deletion_grace_period:deactivation</option> and <option>deletion_grace_period:deletion</option> (<u:bug>45467</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-lib" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-lib</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>In some cases after stopping the exam mode, shares on the school server weren't accessible anymore. This bug has been fixed (<u:bug>43089</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>When creating a new school, the DHCP server objects for the administrative DC Slave are now also created or moved into the DHCP service of the school in a multiserver environment (<u:bug>42687</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>A incomplete LDAP filter was fixed. Due to relaxed filter parsing, this resulted in no observable error (<u:bug>45504</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>An internal improvement of the &ucsUAS; library: support was added for changing the base path when searching for hooks (<u:bug>45024</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>An internal improvement of the &ucsUAS; library: LDAP object classes for user objects are made available for permission checks during imports (<u:bug>45044</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-info" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-info</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>The CLI tool <command>ucs-school-info</command> does not crash anymore when displaying network information (<u:bug>45229</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>
			<section id="changelog:ucsschool:ucs-school-umc-users" lang="en">
				<title>Source package ucs-school-umc-users</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><simpara>A traceback in the UMC module is prevented that was triggered if the logged in user has no permissions to reset another users password (<u:bug>45255</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

					<listitem><simpara>Special extended attributes are not anymore reset after changing user passwords. The error handling of the module has been improved (<u:bug>45468</u:bug>).</simpara></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
			</section>

		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>
